Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is קו, kuf
vav, 106. We pick up at the bottom of קה עמוד ב
kuf heh amud bet because the משנה mishna mentioned שני דייני גזירות
shnei dayanei gezeirot and there was also the discussion about how they
got paid, we turn to a conversation relating to שוחד shochad and
most recently we were discussing the issue of שוחד דברים shochad devarim
even not through money but through favors, although we did point out
that in all the cases
when the favors were being done there was also an explicit reference
to the fact that they were coming that the people were going
to be seeing them in judgment, so that does raise interesting questions
of what the context was. Anyway, we pick up with about seven
lines from the bottom, three lines before the lines get wide, the
two dots.
רב ענן אייתי ליה ההוא גברא כנתא דגילדני דבגילי. Rav Anan aytei
lei hahu gavra kanta degildani deveigilei. So רב ענן, Rav Anan, a
certain person brought him like a basket of small little fish. אמר
ליה מה עבידתך? Amar lei mai avidatich? What, you know, what are
you doing or what brings you here? אמר ליה דינא אית לי.
Amar lei dina it lei. Yeah, 'cause I'm coming this way 'cause
I've got a judgment. So again, doing the favor and then also
explicitly mentioning the fact, being a little transparent, that he was going
to be seeing him later in the court. לא קביל מיניה. Lo
kabil minei. He didn't accept the gift. אמר ליה פסילנא לך לדינא.
Amar lei psilna lach ledina. You have invalidated me to be a
judge for you. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So he said to him:
דינא דמר לא בעינא. Dina demar lo beina. Fine, I don't want
you to judge me. I'll go to another judge. קבוליה לקבליה מר
Kabulyei likablayei mar so דלא למנע מר מקרובי ביכורים. delo limna mar
mikiruvei bikurim. At least accept the gift 'cause in the stories before
we heard that as a matter of principle not only did they
not judge the cases but they refused to receive the gifts, even
though those two, you know, you should be able to do one
without the other, but here so here he was going to refuse
the gift as well and he said: "Okay, fine, don't judge me,
but at least let me do this מצוה mitzvah and give you,
you know, you this תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, let me give you
this gift." And he compared it to giving ביכורים. bikurim. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a
ברייתא: braita: ואיש בא מבעל שלישה ויבא לאיש האלהים לחם בכורים עשרים
לחם שערים וכרמל בצקלונו.
Ve'ish ba
miba'al
shalisha vayavei le'ish ha'elohim lechem bikurim esrim lechem se'orim vecharmel betziklono. Okay,
so he brought all these things to
אלישע Elisha that's called the bread of
ביכורים. bikurim. וכי אלישע אוכל ביכורים הוה? Vichi Elisha ochel bikurim hava?
Did אלישע Elisha eat ביכורים? bikurim?
So רש״י Rashi tries to prove that אלישע Elisha wasn't a כהן.
kohen. תוספות Tosafot says you don't need to say that, they weren't
in ירושלים Yerushalayim and they weren't bringing a, it wasn't being brought
to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. אלא לומר לך, Ela lomar lach,
to tell you: כל המביא דורון לתלמיד חכם כאילו מקריב ביכורים, Kol
hameivi doron letalmid chacham ke'ilu makriv bikurim, anybody who brings a gift
to a
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is like the bringing of ביכורים. bikurim. Okay,
keep that in mind everybody, okay?
I've got a birthday coming up every day, any day is acceptable.
Anyway, so אמר ליה. amar lei. Now,
by the way, what is interesting, what is worth pointing out I
should say, is, you know, the way in which חז״ל, Chazal, I
mean this was during the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I mean not
this story, but the story of אלישע Elisha was, but the way
in which, you know, חז״ל Chazal deal with the absence of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and then the sort of substitutes for it,
and I think most pronounced about that is the idea that the
same way there's a מצוה mitzvah of עליה לרגל, aliyah laregel, the
גמרא Gemara says there's a מצוה mitzvah to be מקבל פני רבו
ברגל, mekabel pnei rabo baregel, and the רבי rebbi becomes, I mean
I don't know if you remember in the beginning of
מסכת חגיגה, Masechet Chagigah, that whole profound event where they went and
they, you know, they saw this blind רב rav and it was
in the whole context of the עליה לרגל, aliyah laregel, that blind
people aren't עולה לרגל, oleh laregel, but then they did this קבלה
kabbalah and, you know, in terms of a blind person מי שרואה
ואינו נראה. mi sheroyeh ve'eino nir'eh. Anyway, but about that whole thing
about presenting oneself to the רב rav and being מקבל פני רב
mekabel pnei rav as the substitute of, you know, being עולה לרגל.
oleh laregel. And actually it's a little bit even indicated already in
the פסוקים pesukim
by, you know, by the story here by אלישע, Elisha, right? It's,
this is by אלישע, Elisha, right? When it's, no, who was it?
It was, yeah, it was the,
the mother of the, of the boy who died, right? And the
husband says to what? Yeah, השונמית, HaShunamit, right. And the husband says
to her: מדוע את הלכת אליו היום לא חדש ולא שבת? Madua
at holechet elav hayom lo chodesh velo shabbat? Right, which first of
all indicated number one that they used to travel on שבת, shabbat,
but okay, it was that they would, one of the things that
they would do is that they would go to the איש אלהים,
ish elohim, they would go to some, you know, holy man on
שבת shabbat and make it a religious day and spend the day
in communion with God through being with this holy man. And then
you have much later in ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, right, the פסוק pasuk which
is: והיה מדי חודש בחדשו ומדי שבת בשבתו יבוא כל בשר להשתחוות
לפני. Vehaya midei chodesh bechodsho umidei shabbat beshabbato yavo kol basar lehishtachavot
lefanai. Right? מדוע את הלכת אליו היום לא חדש ולא שבת? Madua
at holechet elav hayom lo chodesh velo shabbat? So the idea of
that man of God, you know, representing or just substitute for, and
that was even at the time that there was a בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, you know, and that becomes obviously very powerful post-בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash realities. So anyway, so here he's saying... The same thing,
that bringing a gift to a, you know, to a rabbi or
to a holy man or whatever is like the bringing of ביכורים.
bikkurim. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לומר לך, ela lomar lach,
to tell you, כל המביא דורון לתלמיד חכם, kol hamevi doron l'talmid
chacham, anybody who brings a gift to a Torah sage, כאילו מקריב
ביכורים, k'ilu makriv bikkurim, it's like the bringing of ביכורים. bikkurim. So
at least let me do this even if you're not going to
be in judgment. אמר לו, amar lo, קיבלנא לא בעינא דאיקבל. kibalna
lo baina d'ikabel. You know, I didn't want to accept the gift.
Maybe again because it would just set a bad precedent as a
matter of principle, because it was connected to the idea of being
in judgment, just looks wrong, so I wasn't going to accept it.
השתא דאמרת לי טעמא, hashta d'amart li ta'ama, now that you gave
me a good argument and a good reason, and you know, it
was not maybe it also frees it from the potential שוחד shochad
context because it makes it about something completely different, מקבלנא, mikabelna, then
I will accept it.
Okay, but I won't judge you. But look, the story isn't over.
שדרייה, shadreye, so he still needed to be judged. Now if you
remember the previous stories, when the rabbis recused themselves they gave two
Torah sages over to sit in judgment. Here he sent him to
his other another rabbi. שדרייה לקמיה דרב נחמן, shadreye l'kamei d'Rav Nachman,
he sent him to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. He said, "Yeah, go
to רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, he'll listen to your case, fine." שלח
ליה, shlach lei, and he sent to רב נחמן Rav Nachman the
following message: דייניה למר להאי גברא, dayneye l'mar l'hai gavra,
you should, you know, hear this person's case, דאנא אנן פסילנא ליה
לדינא, d'ana Anan pasilna lei l'dina, because I, אנן, Anan, רב אנן,
Rav Anan,
I am invalid to be a witness, a judge for him. So,
there are multiple reasons why you could be invalid as a judge,
why you would have to recuse yourself. So אמר, amar, so רב
נחמן Rav Nachman when he got this message said, מדשלח לי הכי,
mideshlach li hachi, since he sent me this message, שמע מינה קריביה
הוא, shma mina kriveye hu, it must be he's a relative and
that's why he had to recuse himself. הוה קא דיינא דינא דיתמי
קמיה, hava ka daina dina d'yasmei kamei, so there was a, he
was, there was a case of orphans that he was, that was
present in front of him, he was dealing with a case relating
to orphans. But then he got this letter, "Listen to this guy's
case, I can't judge it." So he figured that that meant that
it was a relative. So אמר, amar, he said, האי עשה והאי
עשה. hai aseh v'hai aseh. I have two positive מצוות mitzvahs here.
One מצווה mitzvah to judge the case of the orphans, you know,
right now. And the question is what מצווה mitzvah is it? So
רש״י Rashi says just a general מצווה mitzvah ושפטתם צדק. ushfatetem tzedek.
The מהרש״א Maharsha also says there's a מצווה mitzvah right about like
לא תכירו פנים במשפט כקטן כגדול תשמעון. lo takiru panim bamishpat k'katon
k'gadol tishm'un. So,
you know, maybe דווקא davka to particularly pay attention to the ones
of the orphans and not give any weight to this person he
thought was רב אנן's Rav Anan relative.
It's generally to have compassion for the orphans.
Well, yeah,
that's an interesting question in terms of, right, in terms of the
impartiality of justice and how that plays in. But anyway, but there's
another opposite מצוות עשה, mitzvat aseh, which is the כבוד תורה, kavod
Torah, because he figured to listen to this relative's case first is
showing כבוד kavod to רב אנן Rav Anan indirectly and giving כבוד
kavod to תורה. Torah. So סליק לדינא דיתמי ואחתי לדיניה. salik l'dina
d'yasmei v'achtei l'dineye. So he removed the case of the orphans, he
put that on hold, and he went first to hear this guy's
case. כיוון דחזא בעל דיניה יקרא דקא עביד ליה,
keivan d'chaza ba'al dineye
yakra d'ka avid lei, so now when his, you know, the litigant,
the, you know, the, the person who was, who was, who was
siding with him in the case, saw, "Oh my God, look at
this. The, you know, רב נחמן Rav Nachman is, is leaving the
case of the orphans to hear this person's case because he knows
he's רב אנן's Rav Anan relative." So it, it made him feel
that this person was going to be totally favored. And therefore איסתתם
טענתיה. istatam tanateye. So his, he, you know, he was silenced. He,
you know, he silenced himself, but he did not feel free to
really fully, you know, articulate his claim and his position because he
felt that the deck was stacked against him, that this guy's already
inclined towards this person because he's רב אנן's Rav Anan relative. So
this is a very powerful story, of course, because it shows not
just the earlier stories. You know, the earlier stories where you take
a bribe, even when you refuse a bribe, but because this person
offered you a bribe, remember even though he didn't hear the case
he was going around saying, "Oh he could've said this, he could've
said that." And you know the power it exerts on you even
subconsciously to incline you towards a certain person. Here, right, he didn't
even get a bribe. He didn't, he, you know, he just thought
that this person was somebody else's relative, and even so, and he
wasn't trying to show favor to this person, he was trying to
show favor to רב אנן. Rav Anan. But even that little thing,
and maybe it wasn't so little, you know, what impact does that
have to the other side? And what messages is it sending, and
how does it possibly pervert the justice even something that was done
completely, you know, for good reason, you know, for like right reasons,
but what's the, you know, what's the power of the acts that
get communicated? And you know, this actually does happen because I've heard
cases about people that have gone to women that have gone to
cases of, to בתי דין, batei din, you know, for, for גט.
get. Even when it wasn't sometimes it was contentious, you know, but
even when it wasn't, but sometimes it דווקא davka was and there
were potential like גט get withholding and עגונה agunah issues and so
on. And these are, and this was even about a בית דין
beis din that generally has a reputation for being like one of
the best בתי דינים batei dinim that, you know, around for this
type of a thing. But the thing is first of all, you
know, the woman goes in and it's like all men and she's
the one woman. So already what does that do to, you know,
make a person not feel comfortable to really, you know, state their
case? But then I've heard stories where like, you know, it happened
to be that the דיינים dayanim had gone to ישיבה yeshiva with
the guy. and they went up and they said, "Oh, שלום עליכם,
Shalom Aleichem, how are you?" whatever, and all of a sudden what
does that do to completely skew, you know, the dynamics and the
and the even in their mind and even if they will themselves
be able to be impartial, which was the story before that the
judge wouldn't be able to be impartial, how does their actions affect
the other, you know, affect the people that are there arguing their
case and implicitly silence them? So very powerful story here even beyond
these the cases of שוחד. Shochad. Yes.
So can I learn from here that in in this type of
situation and power situation גבאי דכבוד תורה אינו יעדי? Gabbai de-Kavod Torah
eino ya'adi?
No, I think what you can learn is that it's when it's
dealing with cases of of of court and judging that the most
right, that you have to put aside, that the most important thing
is not to act in any way that can skew right, exactly,
exactly.
גבאי דכבוד תורה, Gabbai de-Kavod Torah, you see that has to actually
take a back seat.
Exactly, to exactly, to make sure that it's as not only it's
impartial in the eyes of the judges, but that the right, the
right, the culture and the messages and whatever are done in a
completely objective way.
Isn't there an issue of חלישות הדעת? Chalishut ha-Da'at? I mean like
if he was in the middle of a case how can he
just?
Alright, well that's not חלישות הדעת, Chalishut ha-Da'at, but anyway, but yeah,
okay, so that's part of the problem, that's part of problematic about
what he's done. And if you look the מהרש"א Maharsha brings in
discussions in סנהדרין Sanhedrin about whether exactly,
you know, what obligation he had here. But let's take a look
as the
the way the story is set up, it was the בעל דין
Ba'al Din
didn't know
that that רב נחמן Rav Nachman thought that this guy was a
relative of רב ענאן, Rav Anan, right? So it just looks like
total favoritism. "Who is
this guy?" I see. Well, no, because no, no because if you
think about that that he didn't have any context, then all that
happened was was that he said, "Okay, we're gonna listen to you
guys first." There obviously was something that signaled that it was because
of this guy, not because of the case, right? So it must
have been, "Oh, well you brought a letter from רב ענאן Rav
Anan and I'll listen to your case first." But you're right, but
it didn't say that why because he thought he was a relative,
but there was something that was communicated the idea it was because
of this guy, not because of the two of them, right? But
you're right, it wasn't necessarily because he assumed he was a relative,
"Oh, he's got a letter from רב ענאן, Rav Anan, and let
me listen to your case." And you're right, who knows, maybe the
other guy put two and two together, he said he came with
a letter from רב ענאן Rav Anan and I saw רב נחמן
Rav Nachman took his gift. You know, maybe he assumed that's what
it was about. But right. But in the end I don't think
it would have mattered even if he thought it was a relative,
that would have made him feel that it wasn't going to be
biased? You know, look at what you did because it was a
relative, I wonder what you're going to do during the case itself.
All right, so now we have רב ענאן, Rav Anan, now the
story isn't over though, because רב ענאן Rav Anan is now going
to have to deal with the consequences of his actions of even
his unintentional actions.
רב ענאן הוי רגיל אליהו דאתי גביה. Rav Anan havei ragil Eliyahu
de-ati gabei. רב ענאן Rav Anan used to have אליהו Eliyahu come
visit him. דהוה מתני ליה סדר דאליהו. De-havei matni lei Seder de-Eliyahu.
He taught him the סדר דאליהו Seder de-Eliyahu which is a it's
a collection of whatever of stories from you know about about what
אליהו Eliyahu of stories about אליהו Eliyahu and teachings from
אליהו הנביא. Eliyahu ha-Navi. Yeah. Yeah. סדר אליהו רבא וסדר אליהו זוטא.
Seder Eliyahu Rabba ve-Seder Eliyahu Zuta. We'll actually see in a minute.
Yeah. Exactly. So he taught him those. כיון דעבד הכי, Keivan de-avad
hachi, once רב ענאן Rav Anan did this, right presumably sent this
letter, and again רב ענאן Rav Anan wasn't intentionally trying to do
anything, but that's sometimes the problem, the problem isn't what you intentionally
do, it's what you weren't thinking about and the consequences of those
actions. So once רב ענאן Rav Anan did this,
איסתלק, Istalek, so אליהו Eliyahu removed himself. יתיב בתעניתא, Yativ be-ta'anita, so
רב ענאן Rav Anan sat in a fast. He, you know, he
accepted a fast upon himself.
ובעי רחמי ואתא. U-va'ei rachamei ve-ata. And then אליהו Eliyahu returned. כי
אתא, Ki ata, when אליהו Eliyahu returned, הוה מבעית ליה בבעותיה. Havei
miv-it lei be-vuta'ei. He was like scared of אליהו, Eliyahu, maybe after
the result of him having removed himself. ועבד תיבותא. Ve-avad teivuta. He
made a box ויתיב קמיה. ve-yativ kamei. And he sat in the
box. I don't exactly get that point how that dealt with his
fear. But anyway, עד דאפיק ליה סידריה, ad de-afik lei sidrei, until
אליהו Eliyahu finished teaching him his whole סדר, Seder, the teaching. והיינו
דאמרי, Ve-hainu de-amri, and that's where we say that there's something called
סדר אליהו רבא Seder Eliyahu Rabba and סדר אליהו זוטא, Seder Eliyahu
Zuta, the big one and the small one. So what does that
mean the big one and the small one? So רש"י Rashi says
it means the big one is
שלמד חוץ לתיבה, she-lamad chutz le-teiva, סדר אליהו זוטא Seder Eliyahu Zuta
שלמד בתוך התיבה. she-lamad be-toch ha-teiva. And רש"י Rashi doesn't exactly say
why. תוספות Tosafot says because first he had taught him most of
the teaching beforehand, דאמר רבי לפי שהפסיק בלימודו לרב ענאן נחלקו לשני
סדרים ובפעם ראשון למד ממנו יותר מן ארבע ידות קרי לראשון סדר
אליהו רבא ולבסוף קרי זוטא.
De-amar Rabbi lefi she-hifsik be-limudo le-Rav Anan nechleku li-shnei sedarim u-ve-fa'am rishon
lamad mimenu yoter min arba yadot
kari le-rishon Seder Eliyahu Rabba u-le-vasof kari Zuta. Okay, so the bigger
teaching before the box was אליהו רבא, Eliyahu Rabba, the smaller quantity
was זוטא, Zuta, but maybe it also means that the second one
was of somehow of maybe you know of lesser stature, lesser quality.
Now the מהרש"א Maharsha says the two things that happened here: the
תענית Ta'anit was כנגד keneged the fact that he accepted the fish,
right, so he accepted that, even though he accepted it because he
said, "You can't stop me from being ביכורים," Bikkurim, but this is
now recognizing he shouldn't have accepted the fish. And somehow the sitting
in the box or the trembling was countering the fact that he
sort of made the other בעל דין Ba'al Din tremble. of his
actions, right, the guys, the litigant was afraid to express his own
thoughts, his own and his own position, so that sort of force,
that sort of was the counterbalance by or, the מידה כנגד מידה
mida keneged mida was the trembling he now had. Also, of course,
the lesson could be that he sees what it means when you
are like when when you have a feel a distance from somebody,
you know, how that impacts your own, he now complained from him
and he trembled and he had to create a barrier and he
had to create a box, I think it sends a good message
about how sometimes your actions might influence another side and how and
have that impact about silencing them and making them pull back.
And what it means to be judged and
to be oh yeah that's also a good point ah so he
was with him but like maybe he couldn't he couldn't have the
conversation with the give and take
with אליהו Eliyahu anymore he couldn't have אליהו Eliyahu judge him ah
that's a good point also right what it means to be in
that vulnerable position about being judged by someone right on the other
side and
אליהו Eliyahu exactly what
he did
right right very good okay very good so now the גמרא Gemara
continues okay בשני דרב יוסף bishnei deRav Yosef in the years of
רב יוסף Rav Yosef הוי רתחא havei ritcha there was anger divine
anger which means that there was a famine. אמרו ליה רבנן לרב
יוסף Amru leh rabanan leRav Yosef so the rabbis said to רב
יוסף Rav Yosef ניבעי רחמי nibaye rachamei pray for us pray to
God that he should remove the famine. אמר להו השתא מה לאלישע
Amar lehu hashta mah l'Elisha so here's the תענית Taanis to אלישע
Elisha what was the case with
אלישע Elisha דהוו רבנן מפטרי מקמיה de'havi rabanan miftari mikamei that when
the rabbis would leave learning תורה Torah from אלישע Elisha all the
great personages in the in the תנ"ך Tanach were always rabbis so
you have to understand.
So הוו פיישי תרי אלפין ומאתן רבנן havei payshei trei alfein u'masan
rabanan there would still be even when like the ישיבה yeshiva is
over and סדר seder was over for the day 2,200 rabbis stayed
in the בית מדרש beis medrash learning with אלישע Elisha I have
no idea. ואפילו ברתחא Ve'afilu biritcha and even so at a time
of I have no idea we're actually we're actually gonna quote a
פסוק pasuk in a minute. Okay at the time of divine anger
לא בעי רחמי lo baye rachamei he did not pray to God
to remove the anger I don't know how we know that except
that it's I guess the silence of the תנ"ך Tanach in that
regard. Anyway אנא איבעי רחמי ana ebaye rachamei I should pray to
God?
וממאי דפייש הכי u'mimai depayeish hachi how do you know that there
were so many students in the time of אלישע Elisha דכתיב de'ksiv
that left in the בית מדרש beis medrash ויאמר משרתו vayomer mesharto
and his attendant said ומה אתן זה לפני מאה איש u'mah eten
zeh lifnei meah ish should I give this in front of 100
people מאי לפני מאה איש mai lifnei meah ish what do you
mean in front of 100 people אילימא eilei eimah so this it
if you want it goes back to the פסוק pasuk before where
we had לחם בכורים עשרים לחם שעורים וכרמל lechem bikkurim esrim lechem
seorim ve'karmel so that was
22 presumably loaves עשרים ולחם וכרמל esrim ve'lechem ve'karmel that's 22 loaves.
So he said should I give this in front of 100 people
so what's this the whole 22 loaves? So מאי לפני מאה איש
mai lifnei meah ish אילימא eilei eimah דכולהו de'kulehu all 22 loaves
distributed amongst 100 people לפני מאה איש lifnei meah ish בשני דטובא
טובא הוי bishnei d'tovah tovah havei that would have been a lot
at the time of famine so what's he complaining?
אלא מסתמא דכל חד וחד קמי מאה איש Ela mastamin de'kol chad
ve'chad kamei meah ish each loaf to distribute to 100 people so
if there are 22 loaves and each one is in front of
100 people that's 2,200 people. So there you know that those were
the students that he had to
feed yes no let's just read a little bit more כי הוו
מפטרי רבנן מבי רב ke'havi miftari rabanan mibei rav when the rabbis
would leave the ישיבה yeshiva of רב Rav הוו פיישי אלפא ומאתן
רבנן havei payshei alfa u'masan rabanan there would be
1,200 rabbis students left over in the בית מדרש beis medrash מבי
רב הונא umibei Rav Huna when they left
רב הונא Rav Huna הוו פיישי תמני מאה רבנן havei payshei tamni
meah rabanan 800 rabanan סדרות. sederos. רב הונא הוה דריש בתליסר אמוראי
Rav Huna havei darish bitreisar amorai now רב הונא Rav Huna would
teach with 13 אמוראי amorai now an אמורא amora the same you
know we sometimes talk an אמורא amora is the actual rabbi of
the גמרא Gemara רב הונא Rav Huna רב Rav שמואל Shmuel the
תנא Tanna is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda but
sometimes I sometimes call them lower תנאים Tannaim and lower אמוראים Amoraim
which means the תנא Tanna is the one who teaches over like
the ברייתא brayta תני תנא קמיה ד tani tana kamei de you
know the whatever
and he memorizes them and teaches it over. The אמורא amora is
the one who is the one who actually is like the loudspeaker
okay so the אמורא amora would say something you'd have a big
room the actual whoever it would be the actual teacher would say
something and these people would like yell it out to the room
and they would be the loudspeakers and they'd repeat it to all
the gathered masses. So when he would teach he had 13 אמוראי
amorai he had such a large room of people that he had
all these people that were distributed throughout the room that were along
him that were announcing it to different sections of the room. Okay
כי הוו קיימי רבנן ממתיבתא דרב הונא ke'havi kamei rabanan mimasivta deRav
Huna now when the rabbis would get up from the ישיבה yeshiva
of רב הונא Rav Huna ונפצי גלימייהו venatzi guma'yei and they would
like shake out their garments הוי סליק אבקא havei salik avka and
dust would go up וכסי ליה ליומא ve'kasei leh leyoma and it
would cover over the sun right the day would become dark from
their dust of their garments. ואמרי במערבא Ve'amri b'maarava and they would
say in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael ah קמו להו ממתיבתא דרב הונא
דבבל kamu lehu mimasivta deRav Huna deBavel alright yeah we understand we
know that the day
at the ישיבה yeshiva in רב הונא Rav Huna the Babylonians finished.
Oh, who knows?
He mentioned about the rabbis of the ישיבה Yeshiva of
רבא ורב יוסף.
Rava ve-Rav Yosef. From the rabbis that would leave the ישיבה Yeshiva
of רבא ורב יוסף, Rava ve-Rav Yosef, הוו פיישו ארבע מאה רבנן,
havei paishu arba mei'ah rabbanan, there would be four hundred rabbis left
over. It keeps on going down the number. וקרו לנפשייהו יתמי, ve-karu
le-nafshaihu yasmi, and they called themselves orphans because look at this נעבעך,
nebach, you know, there's only four hundred rabbis that are left staying
around in the ישיבה Yeshiva after the end of the day of
learning as opposed to the previous generations, twenty-two hundred, eight hundred, and
so on. כי הוי מיפטרי רבנן מבי אביי, ki havei miftari rabbanan
mibei Abaye, now when the rabbis would leave the ישיבה Yeshiva of
אביי, Abaye, ואמרי לה מבי רב פפא, ve-amri la mibei Rav Pappa,
and some say the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב פפא, Rav Pappa, ואמרי
לה מבי רב אשי, ve-amri la mibei Rav Ashi, or רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, הוו פיישו מאתן רבנן, havei paishu masan rabbanan, there would
only be two hundred rabbis that would hang around at the end
of the day of learning.
וקרו לנפשייהו יתמי דיתמי, ve-karu le-nafshaihu yasmi de-yasmi, orphans of orphans, you
know, that there's such small amount that are left, you know, as
opposed to what it used to be in previous generations.
You better not be after today. Yeah, you better not be. Yeah,
there was a question before, sorry.
The question was for רב יוסף Rav Yosef wondering whether he should
pray. At least if he didn't pray, he created a miracle to
feed people.
Right. So I mean who needs you to pray if you, right,
maybe that's I don't know, it's a good point.
All right. אמר רב יצחק בר רדיפא אמר אבני. Amar Rav Yitzchak
bar Redifa amar Avani.
Now we're back to our more major theme here about פרק פ"ד,
Perek Peid, right, which led to the whole discussion about accepting bribes.
And I want to remember, so we had mentioned that the דייני
גזירות dayyane gezerot were paid money from the communal funds, and the
question תוספות Tosafot asked is why is that different than the idea
of not being paid for judgment? So the first thing תוספות Tosafot
says, obviously it's free of any concern of bribery because it's not
coming from communal funds, it's not coming from the litigants, it's coming
from communal funds. Fine, but we had a discussion before that you're
not even supposed to get paid from both sides, you know, because
of a problem about getting שכר דין. schar din. And תוספות Tosafot
basically said even there there'd be a difference about being paid from
both sides and being paid communally. Or תוספות Tosafot pointed out a
difference between being paid for the service as opposed to being freed
from having to do any job and just being generally supported by
the community. So that was but that was the idea of the
idea of some of these services being paid by communal funds. And
now we return to that theme. So let's take a look.
אמר רב יצחק בר רדיפא אמר אבני, Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Redifa
amar Avani, מבקרי מומין שביירושלים, mevakrim mumin she-be-Yerushalayim, those in ירושלים Yerushalayim
that it would be their job to check out the blemishes in
sacrifices, היו נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה, hayu notlin secharam mi-terumat ha-lishka, they
would be paid from the תרומת הלשכה, terumat ha-lishka, money collected for
the קרבנות korbanot and when there would be leftover funds there they
would also use it for other types of services, temple-related or you
know other you know communal-related services. So this actually is very much
קרבן korban related. So anyway they were they would be paid, you
know, from those funds. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel, תלמידי חכמים המלמדים הלכות שחיטה לכהנים, talmidei chachamim ha-melamdim hilchot
shechita le-kohanim, not only that, but even the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
that would teach the כהנים kohanim how to do שחיטה, shechita, היו
נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה, hayu notlin secharam mi-terumat ha-lishka, reminds you a
little bit about those stories in the beginning of יומא Yoma about
how they would teach the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol how to do
the עבודה avoda or whatever. היו נוטלין שכרם מתרומת הלשכה, hayu notlin
secharam mi-terumat ha-lishka, they also would be paid from the תרומת הלשכה
terumat ha-lishka and this is all seen as צרכי קרבן. tzorchei korban.
אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav Giddel amar Rav, תלמידי חכמים
המלמדים הלכות קמיצה לכהנים, talmidei chachamim ha-melamdim hilchot kemitza le-kohanim, those that
would teach the כהנים kohanim how to do קמיצה, kemitza, נוטלין שכרם
מתרומת הלשכה, notlin secharam mi-terumat ha-lishka, also be paid from these communal
funds the תרומת הלשכה terumat ha-lishka that was collected annually for the
קרבנות.
korbanot. Doesn't the כהונה kahuna hand these things?
Yeah, that is true. I think that's why it's talking about הלכות
hilchos as opposed to the actual physical skill, right? So the skill
you can teach, but like somebody's
קבלה kabbala from the skill, but you have to learn the הלכה.
halacha.
Exactly, exactly. The Rebbe may teach the skill, but what exactly happens
in this scenario and in that scenario and whatever, so I think
that that's why you're right. I mean it's not about the מעשה
שחיטה maaseh shechita or the מעשה הקטרה, maaseh haktara, right, or the
קמיצה, kemitza, it's the הלכות, hilchos, right. But isn't although there isn't
are they trying to say that there isn't a problem in terms
of charging for a מצוה? mitzva?
Yeah, so when we learn שקלים, Shekalim, no, the גמרא Gemara here
is not getting to the charging point. That was תוספות's Tosafot discussion
earlier, right, and תוספות Tosafot said again that maybe it's you know
because once they're devoting their all their time to this then they're
not directly being paid, you know, it's a type of a שכר
בטלה schar battala and they're not directly being paid for the service,
they're being paid, you know, because the community is supporting them, although
it doesn't say that. It sounds like it's שכרא, sechara, it's actually
a fee, but anyway.
Okay, so now let's continue though it says I think there's another
small תוספות Tosafot that makes the same point here.
No. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, says like this. אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabba bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan, מגיהי ספרים שביירושלים, maggihei sefarim she-be-Yerushalayim,
those that would proof the ספרי תורה sifrei Torah presumably, היו נוטלין
שכרם מתרומת הלשכה, hayu notlin secharam mi-terumat ha-lishka, they would get their
fee from תרומת הלשכה. terumat ha-lishka. That's more interesting because that is
not really related to the קרבנות, korbanot, but as we're going to
see as we continue דף daf and as you might remember when
we did שקלים, Shekalim, some of that money, particularly if it was
שירי תרומת הלשכה, shiyarei terumat ha-lishka, not always clear whether we're talking
about the תרומה truma or the שיריים shirayim of the תרומה truma
would come also from. monies collected in terms of the תרומת הלשכה.
Terumat HaLishka. Okay, רש"י Rashi specifically notes the problem here and רש"י
Rashi says ורוב בית דין שהיו מתעצלים בדבר והפקירו תרומת הלשכה לכך.
V'rov Beit Din SheHayu Mit'atzlim BeDavar VeHifkiru Terumat HaLishka LeKach.
So that's always the out when you're doing with this. לב בית
דין מתנה עליהן. Lev Beit Din Matne Aleihen. Even if technically this
is not a legitimate use of those funds, there's always that overriding
stipulation, we have the,
we reserve the right to use the funds as we see fit
even though they're being given for the קרבנות Korbanot and anybody who
gives the money gives it with the understanding that we can reassign
it as necessary. Being lazy? The people were not checking their own
ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah.
Okay, so therefore, I didn't know how most of them, could be.
Doesn't mean they weren't bringing it to סופרים Sofrim to check it
either. Okay. All right, but so, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה: Amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabbah bar Avuha: נשים האורגות בפרוכת נוטלות
שכרן מתרומת הלשכה.
Nashim HaOrgoth BaParochet Notlot
Secharan MiTerumat HaLishka.
The women who would be weaving the פרוכת, Parochet, right, for the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, they would also get their money from the
תרומת הלשכה. Terumat HaLishka. Now is that really related to the קרבנות
Korbanot or is that really related to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
proper, the structure proper, which would more be about בדק הבית? Bedek
HaBayis? So we're going to see about that in a minute about
the whole discussion about בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayis. So let's take a
look.
I'm so skeptical about the רב Rov not keeping around ספרי תורה,
Sifrei Torah, I mean like, as early as the twenty.
Yeah, you know, yeah, so I mean, you know, whatever they, that's
why you put the גארטל Gartel on the outside so it's a
סימן, Siman, so exactly, exactly. Yeah, I mean and there's also discussions
in the ש"ך Shach and ט"ז Taz about like is it the
same thing when we're not actually learning from it? Because you might
say, I mean for us we relate to the whole thing purely
as a ritual object. We might say, oh my God, you'll be
making like a ברכה לבטלה Beracha LeVatala or whatever. But the bigger
concern is that you actually understand the divine word wrong than it
was meant, right? If it becomes a ספר לימוד Sefer Limud not
just a type of a ritual ספר. Sefer. But yeah, so there's
a discussion about that. All right, so it says like this, נשים
האורגות בפרוכת, Nashim HaOrgoth BaParochet, נוטלין שכרן מתרומת הלשכה, Notlin Secharan MiTerumat
HaLishka, ואני אומר מקדשי בדק
הבית.
VeAni Omer
MiKodshei Bedek HaBayis.
And I say no, from the funds that go to fixing up
the actual structure of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
for good reasons, because מקדשי בדק הבית: MiKodshei Bedek HaBayis: הוא פרוכת
תחת בנין עשויות. Hu Parochet Tachas Binyan Asuyot.
It's made underneath the actual structure. Now what it means under is
because they are, it is actually part of the, part of the
structure that's roofed, right? The roofed part is the, right? Everybody remember
from when we learned
this, אולם, Ulam, right, היכל, Heichal, right here, והדביר, VeHaDvir, right, that's
the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Okay, and then you've got the open
courtyard. This part here is all, I mean you don't see it
normally when you draw two-dimensionals, you know, but that's all roofed. Okay,
and this is all open air. You need the basically the מזבח
Mizbeiach to be open air because you do not want all the
smoke from the sacrifices caught under a roof. Okay, here all you
basically have is like the מזבח הזהב Mizbeiach HaZahav and you have
the מנורה, Menorah, right? So anyway, so this is all under a
roof. So sorry, whoops, thank you. Okay.
Right, and the שולחן, Shulchan, okay, fine. So anyway, so here's the
understanding, right? Do you consider a פרוכת Parochet to be part of
the structure or not? Like obviously if you were spending money building
the walls of the חצר Chatzer here, that would be בדק הבית.
Bedek HaBayis. But if you're just putting up a freestanding, you know,
a curtain, is that considered to be structural or is that considered
to be more like let's say a כלי, Kli, you know, I
mean it's freestanding or whatever, I mean maybe it's hooked on. You
know, it's actually interesting we're learning that in הלכות שבת. Hilchos Shabbos.
There are some that say if you have a doorway, an open
doorway, and you hook on a curtain on it to serve as
a doorway, so there are some that says that it's מותר Mutar
to do that on שבת, Shabbos, because you're just like putting something
on your wall like hanging up a picture on your wall. And
others say, the חזון איש, Chazon Ish, which to me makes the
most sense, says, what the heck are you talking about? You put
a curtain on your doorway, you're like making a door, you're like
adding to the structure, you know, you're not just, it's not a
hanging on the building, it becomes part of the building, it becomes
a doorway. Okay, so that actually, you know, is, I mean sometimes
I think some pictures also become like integrated into the wall, you
know, but that's the question: if there's something that's just hanging on
the wall it's allowed, but if like if you were to make
a window dressing, hang up a window dressing on שבת, Shabbos, that
would actually be adding something to your, you know, become part of
the building, not just something hanging from the building.
Do you mean the logic is that the walls of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash don't have the קדושה Kedusha of a כלי? Kli?
The walls of,
in other words you make a distinction between structural and a כלי?
Kli?
Right, because yeah what we're going to get to the כלים, Keilim,
the כלים Keilim are seen as different than the בדק הבית. Bedek
HaBayis.
Right, but wouldn't a כלי Kli that's
being
served by the בנין Binyan be more קודש? Kodesh?
I don't know more קודש, Kodesh, it comes from different funds. The
question is, does it come, we're going to see but what funds
the כלים Keilim come from. But the question is to use the
funds of בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayis, okay, it seems to be something
structural. So the question is, is the פרוכת Parochet considered part of
the structure or not? Yeah.
Yeah. He just said brings into question the common practice including
Right, so that's less of an issue because it's not actually physically
attached to a wall. Okay, I'm not going to get into putting
up מחיצות *Mechitzas* on שבת *Shabbos* and whether that's אהל *ohel* or
whatever. Anyway, but the problem is actually the point being that generally
that's not so much of an issue unless you incorporate it into
the physical structure itself of a בנין *Binyan*. And that's interestingly what
is sort of being said here at saying is this is actually
done under the roof part, you know, then that's much more a
part of the בנין *Binyan* than just something that's seen as like
a hanging on something. Okay, חוץ ומתחת הבנין עשויות *Chutz u'mitachat habinyan
asuyot*. מיתיבי *Meisivei* on this. נשים האורגות בפרוכות *Nashim ha'orgot beparochos*, women
who are weaving the the curtain. ובית גרמו על מעשה לחם הפנים
Lechem HaPanim? *U'Beis Garmo al ma'aseh lechem hapanim*, and the בית Beit...
גרמו *Beis Garmo* that were the ones that would teach how to
make the bread. ובית אבטינס על מעשה הקטורת *U'Beis Avtinas al ma'aseh
haktoret*, and בית אבטינס *Beis Avtinas* who were the ones who knew
how to do the קטורת ketoret *haktoret*. כולן *Kulan*, all of these
craftsmen or women, היו נוטלות שכרן מתרומת הלשכה *hayu notlot secharan mitrumat
halishka*, would be paid for the from the תרומת הלשכה Terumas HaLishkah
*trumat halishka*. So you see, not from the בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis
*Bedek HaBayis*. So גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, התם בדבבי *Hatam bedivavi*,
that is the curtains that would be on the gates and would
not be under the roofed part, right? So you would have gates
here, right, you'd have gates all along here, right, you'd have these
gates. And those gates would have curtains. So that would actually be
seen more of a כלי kli, *klee* and less as part of
the בית *bias*, as opposed to a curtain hanging from within a
from within opening under a roof. דאמר רב זירא אמר רב *D'amar
Rav Zeira amar Rav*, שלוש עשרה פרוכיות היו במקדש *shelosh esreh parochiyot
hayu bamikdash*, there were thirteen curtains. שבע כנגד שבעה שערים *sheva keneged
shiva shearim*, seven for the seven gates. אחד לפתחו של היכל ואחד
לפתחו של אולם *echad l'pitcho shel heichal v'echad l'pitcho shel ulam*, one
for the opening of the היכל *heichal*, one for the אולם *ulam*.
שתיים בדביר שתיים כנגדן בעלייה *shtayim badvir shtayim kenegdan ba'aliya*.
So here's one in the אולם *ulam*, here's one in the in
the היכל *heichal*. And if people remember from the whole way we
do the עבודה *avoda*, right, you do that, and then it was
a double story so up here too there would be a one
directly above it. Okay, so these are considered to be more part
of the בנין *binyan* than those, and that actually does have a
very interesting parallel and discussions of הלכות שבת *hilchos shabbos*. Okay, but
what you see is if it's not from בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis.
*Bedek HaBayis* it sort of gets defaulted to תרומת הלשכה Terumas HaLishkah,
*trumat halishka*, even though תרומת הלשכה Terumas HaLishkah. *trumat halishka* should be
about קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot*, not all of these are directly about קרבנות
korbanos, *korbanot*, okay? Certainly the one about the ספרי תורה *sifrei Torah*,
I mean you could argue פרוכות *parochos* is a little indirectly although
you don't need the פרוכות *parochot* in the gates in order to
bring קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot*, but okay. תנו רבנן *Tnu rabbanan*, נשים המגדלות
בניהן לפרה *nashim hamigadlot bneihen l'para*, the women that would raise their
kids for the service in the פרה אדומה *para aduma*. It's sort
of like what do they do now, who is it, is it
the Dalai Lama that they take out and he he's raised separate
from society, whatever for many years? What? At a very young age,
right? So they would do this too because they would have these
קולות *kulas* by the פרה אדומה *para aduma*, this leniency in order
to you know in order to sort of like counteract the teachings
of the צדוקים Tzadokim, *tzadokim* that said that he could never be
he couldn't be טמא *tamei* at all, they would intentionally make the
כהן *kohen* who did the burning of the פרה אדומה *para aduma*,
they'd make him טמא *tamei* and then have him go to the
מקווה *mikvah* and he'd be טבול יום *tvul yom* or whatever because
of as a way of showing that there could be a little
bit of טומאה *tumah*, you know, and you gotta love the דרשה
*drasha* of it in the גמרא Gemara *gemara* it says, ואסף איש
טהור *v'asaf ish tahor*, טהור מכלל דהוא טמא *tahor miklal d'hu tamei*.
So means he had just been טמא *tamei* and now he's טהור
*tahor* but he's not fully טהור *tahor*. Anyway because they had that
קולא *kula* to make a point against the צדוקים Tzedukim *tzadokim*, they
went crazy מחמיר *machmir* in the other direction with everything else. So
what they did was was that they would actually go and have
pregnant women, קלוס פאת *koulas bat* where they where it was like
on top of a cave so if there's anybody buried underground the
cave, you know, the cave would stop it and they'd be on
top of the cave, the ceiling of the cave would stop the
טומאה *tumah*, so they'd know they'd be טהור *tahor*, they'd give birth
to their kids in that spot and their whole kids would be
raised their whole lives in that spot to make sure that they
would never become טמא *tamei*, and then those kids would help in
the actual process of preparing, you know, the פרה אדומה *para aduma*
and getting it ready. I know. Well, I don't know how many
they would have ready for that. Anyway, so that's a whole זעסעמען
*zessemen* story with that. נשים המגדלות בניהן לפרה *Nashim hamigadlot bneihen l'para*,
so the women would raise their kids, היו נוטלות שכרן מתרומת הלשכה
*hayu notlot secharan mitrumat halishka*. So it would so actually they got
paid for doing this crazy thing. So they actually some they got
some funds and support also you know who was actually providing them
with the food and all those things, who was helping that financially
make that happen, that was money that came from the תרומת הלשכה
Trumas HaLishka, *trumat halishka*. אבא שאול אומר omer, *Abba Shaul omer*, אבא
שאול *Abba Shaul* said, נשים יקרות שבירושלים היו זנות אותן ומפרנסות אותן
*Nashim yakirot shebi'Yerushalayim hayu zanot otan u'mefarnesot otan*. No, the very you
know wealthy women in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, high society women whatever, they
would go out of their ways to provide food and other means
of support, רש''י Rashi *Rashi* said לבוש וכסות *levush u'chsut*, so that's
sort of like things we're talking about כתובה *ksuba*, right? זן ומפרנס
את אשתו ואת בניו *Zan u'mefarnes es ishto v'es banav*. Anyway, they
would provide it for for those women. You didn't have to come
from תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishka, *trumat halishka*. Okay. בעי מיניה רב הונא
מרב *Ba'ei minei Rav Huna me'Rav*, so רב הונא *Rav Huna* asked
רב *Rav*. It's sort of like the upper classes making you know
having it that the lower classes are the ones that go serve
in the army, you know? So. כלי שרת klei shares, מהו שיעשה
מקדשי בדק הבית? mi-kodshei bedek ha-bayis And
now we've learned that בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis. is basically used only
for the structural things; תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishka. is the catch-all for
everything else. What about the כלי שרת, klei shares. about the vessels?
Do they come from מקדשי בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis or not? צורך
מזבח נינהו? Tzorech mizbe'ach ninhu? They're something that are used in conjunction
with the altar, of bringing the קרבן, korban, ומקדשי בדק הבית אתו?
u-mi-kodshei bedek ha-bayis asu? And therefore they are, you know, it's seen
as connected to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, and the מזבח mizbe'ach is not
a כלי, kli I mean it's huge, so that's actually seen as
part of the structure itself, so these are considered to be like
part of the מזבח mizbe'ach and therefore part of בדק הבית. Bedek
HaBayis או צורך קרבן נינהו, O tzorech korban ninhu, or do we
say no, they're used in the bringing of a קרבן, korban, ומתרומת
הלשכה היו עושים אותם? u-mi-terumas ha-lishkah hayu osim osam? And therefore it
would come from the תרומת הלשכה, Trumas HaLishka which is money that
is about קרבנות. korbanot אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to
him, it comes from the תרומת הלשכה. Trumas HaLishka. All right. איתיביה,
Eisivei, I'll ask you on this. וככלותם הביאו לפני המלך ויהוידע את
שאר הכסף, U-ke-chalosam hevi'u lifnei ha-melech ve-Yehoyada es she'ar ha-kesef,
they brought the remainder of the money that they had gathered for
the, for the בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayis, ויעשו כלים לבית השם כלי
שרת. Vaya'asu keilim le-veis Hashem klei shares. And they used the money
they had gathered for the בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis. to make כלי
שרת. klei shares. So you see it comes from the בדק הבית
Bedek HaBayis money. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him,
דקריך כתובי לא קריך נביאי. De-karich kesuvei lo karich nevi'ei. The person
who taught you כתובי Kesuvei because you quoted from דברי הימים Divrei
HaYamim didn't teach you נביאי, Nevi'ei, because the parallel story in נביאים
Nevi'im in במלכים bi-Melachim says, אך לא יעשה בית השם ספות כסף,
Ach lo ye'aseh beis Hashem safos kesef, I think, ספות, safos, I
think, כלים, keilim, הם למלאכה יתנהו. hem le-melacha yisnehu. They, the money
they collected for the בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayis, they would not use
it for the making of vessels, but they would give it to
the construction workers, the craftsmen who would work on the בדק הבית.
Bedek HaBayis So you don't use it for the vessels. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי קשיין קראי אהדדי. Ei hachi kashyan krayi
ahadadi. Okay, so the פסוקים pesukim contradict themselves. Did the money go
for בדק הבית Bedek HaBayis, or did it go for the כלים?
keilim? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not
difficult. כאן שגבו והותירו כאן שגבו ולא הותירו. Kan she-gavu ve-hosiru kan
she-gavu ve-lo hosiru. In one case, the money that you initially collect
for the בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayis, you do not go ahead and
collect funds for the sake of the כלי שרת. klei shares. The
בדק הבית Bedek Habayis, funds are supposed to be collected only for
the structural aspects, not for the כלי שרת. klei shares, However, if
there was leftover funds after you had done everything
that you needed to do, the leftover money you could use. But
now we've got a problem, because if in principle it's not supposed
to be used, then how do you reassign it if it's leftover?
So the גמרא Gemara, says וכי גבו והותירו מאי הוי? Ve-chi gavu
ve-hosiru mai havei? Who cares if it was leftover? So if it
wasn't, if you're not supposed to use those funds for כלי שרת,
klei shares. so אמר רבי אבהו לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. Amar
Rabbi Abbahu lev beis din masneh aleihem. Oh, once again you always
have that stipulation, right? The בית דין Beis Din stipulates and says
that you know, this money is going for X, but we get
to decide in the end, you know, what's going to happen, you
know, how we'll disperse it if it doesn't get used in the,
in that way. אם הוצרכו הוצרכו, Im hutzrechu hutzrechu,
if they're used for, if they're needed for בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis.
it'll be used for it, for what the intended purpose. ואם לאו
יהיו לכלי שרת, Ve-im lav yehu le-klei shares, they'll go to כלי
שרת. Keilei Shares, Right, it's sort of like you have a, you
know, you have a sign up that says you know, any food
left in the fridge is automatically declared הפקר hefker by the end
of the week, right? So you, you understand what the rules are.
You put your food in the fridge, you understand what the rules
are. You give your money to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, even
though you're giving it for the בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis it's very
clear we in the end get to decide what we're going to
do with it.
Would this be the same thing for the לויים Leviyim who had
to play the instruments? Would that be known as צורך קרבן? tzorech
korban? But it is not...
Yeah, that's a good question. You're making me remember what we learned
in שקלים, Shekalim, which I don't.
Yes, it doesn't fully explain though this, this, in other words what
gave the power, the right to restipulate in that way? Well, look.
The גמרא Gemara assumes, probably historically incorrect, that it was the בית
דין beis din that ultimately had the ultimate authority of what went
on in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, in as opposed to
let's say the כהנים, kohanim, right?
It always has that, that's a huge, what, with the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
and the בית דין? beis din?
Who was the בית דין? beis din?
Like in a judicial sense then or it means like a specific
term? Yeah, I, the sense one gets it that, look, again, historically,
right, historically I imagine that the כהנים kohanim determined what went on
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, not the rabbinic class, right, or
there was tension but that, you know, if it was this was
their purview. When you get it through the eyes of the גמרא,
Gemara ultimately it's always like the rabbis, you know, they're deciding which
כהנים kohanim serve, you know, they're making the rules, everybody, they're overseeing
everything, everything is sort of being, you know, they're supervised by the
rabbis. I don't know if it's concretely the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, I think
it's more the abstract idea, you know. We the rabbis get to
decide what it's all about. So it's stipulating this idea that the,
that the, you know, that the rabbis are the ultimate authorities over
everything
that goes on in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Reminds me that the historical reality is the כהנים kohanim
ran the show and the rabbis were outside grumbling.
Exactly. But the way it, צדוקים, I mean.
Exactly. This is just an idealized version of 300 years later what
the...
that is exactly what I am saying, right? You right, it's
correct. That's my point. It wasn't just that they were כהנים kohanim
and not rabbis, but... It's that they were צדוקים and כהנים Kohanim
and not rabbis. But the גמרא Gemara looks back at it and
imagines that ultimately everything was being sort of supervised and done according
to the rabbinic parameters.
לב בית דין Lev Beis Din means the assumption, whether it's בית
דין כהנים, Beis Din Kohanim, it's not that they had a specific
stipulation where they wrote it down. I think it means it's understood
that you give money to בית דין Beis Din but or to
this fund.
Ultimately it's at their discretion.
Right, but again, so that's true, you're right. I don't think that'd
be articulated. Yeah, I don't think any of this, that there was
a whole long list just sort of saying, okay, if in this
case we're going to use it for this, and this. But you're
right, it's the assumption, we in the end get to decide, in
the end it's our discretion. But still, the phrase of לב בית
דין Lev Beis Din is not לב כהנים מתנה עליהם, Lev Kohanim
Masna Lahem, right? It's לב בית דין מתנה עליהם. Lev Beis Din
Masna Lahem.
But they had בני כהנים גדולים Bnei Kohanim Gedolim in them.
That's true, there've been incursion in the other direction, yeah.
I haven't seen anything in תנ"ך Tanach that actually looks like what
we call rabbis today. And the examples that are given are from
בית ראשון. Bayis Rishon.
Yeah, exactly.
Alright, there you go. Anyway, alright, so it goes like this.
I mean, that's sometimes why it's so powerful the way it's done,
is because it's done
very in an understated way. Meaning it doesn't make a point of
saying, let me explain to you חז"ל. Chazal. No, you know, you
have all these פסוקים, pesukim, yeah, לב בית דין מתנה עליהם, Lev
Beis Din Masna Lahem, right? We just take it for granted that
חז"ל Chazal are really the ones running the whole show here. Alright,
anyway. Okay.
תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael. כלי שרת באין מתרומת הלשכה.
Keilei Shares Ba MiTrumas HaLishka. So now he's saying it's coming from
תרומת הלשכה, Trumas HaLishka, which again is where the גמרא Gemara was
inclined, that fundamentally it does not come from בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis.
so maybe if there's leftover, but in principle it comes elsewhere. It
comes from תרומת הלשכה, Trumas HaLishka. which is the capital. שנאמר, Shenemar,
the verse says, את שאר הכסף. Es Shear Hakesef. The remainder of
the money. So back to the פסוק pasuk before that it seemed
to be talking about the remainder of the money of the בדק
הבית. Bedek Habayis? That's how we interpreted it and we said לב
בית דין מתנה. Lev Beis Din Masna. But now we're saying שאר
הכסף Shear Hakesef actually means the תרומת הלשכה. Trumas HaLishka. Right? Everybody
understands the difference. תרומת הלשכה Trumas HaLishka, was the money everybody gave,
you know, it's why we read שקלים Shekalim right in the beginning
of אדר, Adar, everybody gave the half of the shekel, etc. it
was for the קרבנות, korbanot, but it wasn't used only for the
קרבנות, korbanot it could have been used for related things and then
there's also שירי תרומת הלשכה, Shiurei Trumas HaLishka, which is even used
for a more wider range of things. That's the תרומת הלשכה. Trumas
HaLishka, The בדק הבית Bedek Habayis, is specific funds that were donated
for the building funds of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay?
Was there an annual?
I assumed there was a campaign when they needed to, and otherwise
it was... yeah, we don't ever hear that there was a regular
annual campaign for בדק הבית. Bedek Habayis. It seems like it was
more like ongoing. People would make donations, like הלני המלכה Hilni HaMalka
donated a מנורה, Menorah, you know, other people make other types of
donations. It does not seem like there was a regular annual thing.
I'm sure when they needed to they went and they raised funds.
There was an appreciation, is that הפטרה Haftorah where it's mentioning בדק
הבית?
Bedek HaBayit, מלכים ב יב, Melachim Beis Yud Bais, I'm guessing. Alright,
so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
anyway, okay, so he says that actually was not the remainder of
בדק הבית, Bedek HaBayit it was from the תרומת הלשכה, Trumat HaLishka.
and he learns it from the פסוק pasuk את שאר הכסף, Es
Shear Hakesef, although the context there is money raised for בדק הבית.
Let's take a look. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tana Debei Rabbi Yishmael.
כלי שרת באין מתרומת הלשכה. Keilei Shares Ba MiTrumas HaLishka. שנאמר, Shenemar,
את שאר הכסף. Es Shear Hakesef. איזו כסף שיש לו שיריים? Eizu
Kesef Sheyesh Lo Shiurayim? What is the type of a כסף kesef
that normally has like leftover funds? הוי אומר זה תרומת הלשכה, Hevei
Omer Zeh Trumas HaLishka, the תרומת הלשכה. Trumat HaLishka, And רש"י says
what it means is because at the end of each year you
replenish the funds each year and when the new year comes you
need to use the new funds, so there will always be... I
mean, if you're running a, you know, if you're not running a
deficit spending...
if you're spending your money wisely, at the end of each year
there's going to be unspent funds. And therefore it's something that has
regularly unspent funds. So שאר הכסף Shear Hakesef refers to תרומת הלשכה.
Trumat HaLishka, Okay, so let's take a look. הוי אומר זה תרומת
הלשכה. Hevei Omer Zeh Trumas HaLishka. ואימא
שיריים גופייהו? Ve’eima Shiurayim Gufaihu? So maybe it doesn't mean the תרומת
הלשכה, Trumat HaLishka, maybe it means the שירי תרומת הלשכה, Shiurei Trumas
HaLishka, the leftover amount, right? Since you learned it from the word
שאר הכסף. Shear Hakesef.
So maybe it doesn't mean the initial amount collected directly going for
the כלי שרת, Keilei Shares. but if there's leftover then it can
go for the כלי שרת. klei shareit, So the גמרא Gemara says,
no. כדאמר רבא Kid’amar Rava העולה, Ha’olah, like רבא Rava says by
the פסוק pasuk it says זאת תורת העולה, Zos Toras Ha’olah, to
teach you that all the... that the עולת התמיד Olah HaTamid has
to be brought first and everything afterwards. How do you know the
word העולה Ha’olah refers to the עולה olah of the עולת התמיד?
Olah HaTamid? The ה He says עולה ראשונה, Olah Rishona, the primary
one, the first one, and afterwards all the other קרבנות Korbanot. are
brought. So הכא נמי, hacha nami, here too it says הכסף, Hakesef,
את שאר הכסף. Es Shear Hakesef. כסף ראשון. Kesef Rishon. So it's
the money, it's not the שאר, shear, it is the שאר shear
of the money, it's sort of focusing us on the money itself,
not on the remainder of the money. Anyway, so it comes from
the תרומת הלשכה, Terumat Halishka. not from the שירי תרומת הלשכה. Shiurei
Trumas HaLishka. Alright, so let's... I'll ask you on this. הקטורת וכל
קרבנות ציבור... HaKetores Ve’kol Korbanot Tzibur... הקטורת וכל קרבנות ציבור, Haketoret vechol
korbanot tzibur, the קטורת ketoret and all of the communal sacrifices באין
מתרומת הלשכה, ba'in mitrumat halishka, which is clearly the primary purpose of
the תרומת הלשכה. Terumat Halishka מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach hazahav, the gold altar,
והלבונה. vehalvona. Now there's a question whether we have the word לבונה
levona here, וכלי שרת, veklei shareit, because לבונה levona why isn't that
seen as a type of a קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibur, so there's
a question or on the other hand it's not the same, maybe
it's not exactly the same because
but anyway because it's on the inner, it is on the golden
altar. But anyway, at least the golden altar וכלי שרת veklei shareit
and the other vessels because the golden altar is considered a כלי
because it's more portable than the מזבח mizbeach than the outer מזבח.
mizbeach. So all of those באים ממותאר נסכים ba'im mimotar nesachim come
from the leftover money that was given for the נסכים, nesachim, for
the libations, which is a new concept. What does that mean? So
basically, the short version of it is somebody would donate to bring
flour and wine—you bring a קרבן korban you have to bring flour
and wine of the נסכים nesachim for the קרבן—and korban they would
buy, the הלכה halacha would be that if you have to bring
like a quart, you would buy for an overflowing quart so you
want to be safe, and when you would bring it to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash they'd level it off, and that little
extra would then get saved for הקדש hekdesh purposes. So all those
little extras
eventually total up to a significant amount. We were talking the other
day about all the penny
rounding errors, the penny roundings that the bank does and in the
end it turns out to be real money. So anyway, all of
that extra, all of those funds that were collected from that would
be used for the כלי שרת, klei shareit which is very bizarre
that that is דוקא davka from those funds. It could be that
כלי שרת klei shareit. would not
need regular replacement; it would be maybe that was like a small
amount that was collected and it would be roughly equal to the
amount of money we would need to replace the כלי שרת. klei
shareit I don't know, but I really have no idea what the
logic is.
Does that include like שחיטה shchita knives?
Yes. מזבח העולה, Mizbeach HaOlah, now the outer altar, הלשכות והעזרות, halishkot
veha'azarot, and the chambers and the courtyards, that is באים מבדק הבית.
ba'im mibedek habayit. That's clearly the basic building funds. חוץ לחומת העזרה,
Chutz lechomat ha'azara, באים משירי הלשכה. ba'im mishiyarei halishka.
Now, any type of construction you had to do outside the walls
of the עזרה Azara on the Temple Mount, but that would not
come from the בדק הבית, that would come from
the שירי הלשכה. Shiyarei HaLishka. The שירי הלשכה Shiyarei HaLishka was generally
used for a wide range of communal funds. זו היא ששנינו, Zo
hi sheshaninu, this is what we taught, חומת העיר ומגדלותיה, chomat ha'ir
umigdaloteiha, the walls of the city of ירושלים Yerushalayim and its towers,
וכל צרכי העיר, vechol tzorchei ha'ir, anything relating to sort of ירושלים
Yerushalayim needs,
come from שירי הלשכה. Shiyarei HaLishka. So basically though, bracketing the interesting
question of לבונה, levona, the basic thing that's here unusual is the
כלי שרת klei shareit. and it doesn't come from any of the
two options we were talking about, not בדק הבית and not תרומת
הלשכה, Terumat Halishka it comes from this thing called מותאר נסכים. motar
nesachim. So you see that goes against what we were saying. The
גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, tannai hi, it's a debate of תנאים.
tannaim. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, מותר תרומה motar
truma מה היו עושין בה? ma hayu osin ba? What would they
do with the remainder of the תרומה, truma, like the שירי תרומת
הלשכה? Shiyarei Trumat HaLishka? Again, that was the very big catch-all that
we could do a wide range of things with.
What would we do with that? So we would do ריקועי זהב
ציפוי לבית קודש הקדשים, riku'ei zahav tzipui lebeit Kodesh HaKodashim, various types
of like
golden plating and like filigree that they would do for the inner
chamber of the קודש הקדשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael אומר,
no,
מותר פירות motar perot לקיץ המזבח. lekait hamizbeach. The leftover
fruit—what does leftover fruit mean? We'll see in the גמרא it'll explain
it—that they would use for the keeping the מזבח mizbeach busy. Because
basically if there would be a period in the days or in
the weeks where people weren't bringing קרבנות, it would be an embarrassment.
Nobody's using the מזבח, mizbeach, it's just sitting around, there's no business.
So therefore what they would do is that they would use... it's
sort of like
the when the street performers are whatever they're doing they're playing their
music, they get some people there to give the money that are
like there that are in on it so then other people gather
and give the money. If you're there alone, נבך, nebach, nobody is
there, it's not good for business, it doesn't make it look like
it's a חשוב chashuv thing. So what you have to do is
you have to make sure there are always קרבנות being brought even
if nobody is bringing the קרבן. korban. Okay, so that they would
use therefore the money that they would have from this מותר פירות.
motar perot. We'll see what that means. מותר תרומה, motar truma, the
leftover money of the תרומת הלשכה, Terumat Halishka, לכלי שרת. leklei shareit.
That would be for the כלי שרת. klei shareit So that's similar
to what we said before that the כלי שרת Klei Shareit would
be from, it's not the תרומת הלשכה, Terumat Halishka. at least the
מותר תרומה. motar truma.
לבונה Levona is it only for לחם הפנים? Lechem HaPanim. Is it
no other use?
Yeah, oh, that's true, I actually had misstated it before. I mentioned
לבונה levona in the context of the מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach HaZahav, that
was incorrect. לבונה, Levona, right, the קטורת is מזבח הזהב, Mizbeach HaZahav,
the לבונה levona was לחם הפנים. That is correct, yeah, thank you
for that correction.
So it sounds like the needs of the city of ירושלים Yerushalayim
were taken care of by the בית... Yeah, yeah, or that
independent city government?
So that's an interesting question, right? That's an interesting question. Like what
specifically was ירושלים Yerushalayim? as it relates to the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash or was it all these sort of municipal needs of ירושלים?
Yerushalayim Would it go to the parks, right? You know, I mean
the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim. are very much connected, the whole idea
of like חומה, Choma, the קדושה Kedusha of the מקדש Mikdash is
the חומה Choma of ירושלים. Yerushalayim I mean, so again, I don't
know, would it go to the sewage of ירושלים system and specifically
all
the רגל, Regel, all the extra expense?
Right,
that's true. Yeah, no, it's true. I have to I mean again,
I remember that a lot of this detail is in מסכת שקלים
Masechet Shekalim but I don't remember the specifics.
But yes, they definitely paid for the roads.
Okay, all right. So anyway, so now we have according to this
opinion here, the first opinion, that the כלי שרת Klei Shareit, was
from the מותר Motar of the תרומה, Terumah, of the תרומת הלשכה.
Terumat Halishka? רבי עקיבא אומר מותר תרומה לקיץ המזבח. Rabbi Akiva omer
motar terumah l'kayitz hamizbe'ach. No, the leftover money of the תרומת הלשכה
went to the קיץ המזבח, Kayitz Hamizbe'ach, which makes sense by the
way, because תרומת הלשכה is fundamentally about קרבנות. מותר נסכים, Motar Nesachim,
the leftover money of the נסכים, Nesachim, again when you bought a
little extra for the נסכים Nesachim and you had these little amounts
added up, that would be לכלי שרת. L'klei Shareit. That would be
for the כלי שרת, Klei Shareit and that's what we had
that was the ברייתא Braita we had said earlier, which was that
third idea that the כלי שרת Klei Shareit would come from
the מותר נסכים. Motar Nesachim. רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים אומר מותר נסכים
לקיץ המזבח. Rabbi Chanina Segan Hakohanim omer motar nesachim l'kayitz hamizbe'ach. That
would come for the קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. That, by the way,
does make good logical sense, right? Because this was this was going
on the מזבח. Mizbe'ach.
So the קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. I lost my place. מותר תרומה
לכלי שרת, Motar terumah l'klei shareit, leftover תרומה Terumah לכלי שרת. L'klei
Shareit. So here again you see two out of the three opinions
is that the כלי שרת would come from the leftover תרומת הלשכה,
which is in line of the idea we were saying before that
it would come from the תרומת הלשכה. And what you do have
is one opinion that said it would be the מותר נסכים, Motar
Nesachim, so you see it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, so
now the גמרא says זה וזה לא היו מודים בפירות. Zeh vezeh
lo hayu modim bepeirot. But neither of them agreed of these last
two opinions, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and
you notice none of the things they said spoke about this leftover
פירות, Peirot, which was the first opinion of what you would do
with the קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. So we have to find out
what is this מותר פירות Motar Peirot and why did they not
feel that you could use any money of מותר הפירות. Motar Hapeirot.
So let's take a look. מאי פירות? Mai peirot? So what פירות
Peirot מאי? Mai? What is this פירות Peirot that the first opinion
said you would use it for קיץ המזבח Kayitz Hamizbe'ach and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina rejected it altogether? דתנו,
Detanu, we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, מותר תרומה
מה היו עושים בה? Motar terumah mah hayu osim bah? What would
you do with the leftover תרומת הלשכה? לוקחין פירות בזול, Lokchin peirot
b'zol, you would
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash would go into business, they buy keep,
they buy fruit on the cheap, ומוכרין אותן ביוקר, Umochrin otan b'yoker,
and sell it when it was more expensive. Everybody know how to
do that, I mean if it was so easy then everybody would
be in business. Okay. והשכר, Vehaschar, and any profits that they would
make, מקיצין בו את המזבח. Makitzin bo et hamizbe'ach. They would use
that money for the קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. So that was the
first opinion. So basically what he would say is is that if
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash had any extra funds, they would invest
it. So you take the money you have and you invest it
and you use the profit for who
were coming they had like a monopoly
on well that would also be true exactly exactly so they're in
a very unique position to make that money and to do well
with it and therefore they would use that they would use the
earnings to do the קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. So basically you would
go to business. One minute. וזו היא ששנינו מותר פירות לקיץ המזבח.
Vezu hi shesheninu motar peirot l'kayitz hamizbe'ach. That's the opinion that said
that you use the money that they make for the קיץ המזבח.
Kayitz Hamizbe'ach. And what does it mean that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and whoever it was רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina
Segan Hakohanim disagreed? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishna, מותר
שירי לשכה מה היו עושים בהן? Motar shirei lishka mah hayu osim
bahen? What would you do with the leftover money from the שירי
לשכה? Shirei Lishka? לוקחין בהן יינות שמנים וסלתות והשכר להקדש דברי רבי
ישמעאל. Lokchin bahen yeinot shemanim uslatot vehaschar lahekdesh divrei Rabbi Ishmael.
So here now it even makes more sense and this is what
this is what it would say, it's not just some fruit, it's
not like we would sell pomegranates. Okay, we would buy the stuff
that we were in a unique position to know that people need
and they were coming to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and they
need them right, so we had like a monopoly and we had
a captive audience and so we could make a pretty penny by
by buying all this stuff up and selling it on the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash ground. Okay, that's what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael said
and you'd use the money to help in the operating expenses of
the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. רבי עקיבא אומר אין משתכרין בשל הקדש.
Rabbi Akiva omer ein mishtakrin beshel hekdesh.
You do not use הקדש Hekdesh money to make a profit.
הקדש Hekdesh can't profit, meaning they didn't go into business.
They did not go into business. אף לא בשל עניים, Af lo
beshel aniyim, and also not money of the poor. בשל הקדש מאי
טעמא, Beshel hekdesh mai ta'ama, why not by הקדש? Hekdesh? אין עניות
במקום עשירות. Ein aniyut bimkom ashirut. It's disrespectful of הקדש Hekdesh that
they have to they're supposed to be like the source of all
wealth and whatever now they have to actually get into the dirty
business of making money. ובשל עניים מאי טעמא, Uv'shel aniyim mai ta'ama,
and why not for the poor? דילמא מיתרמי להו עני וליכא למיתב
ליה. Dilma mitrami lehu ani veleika lemitav leh. Because maybe a poor
person you'll have their money invested and a poor person will need
the money immediately to be available. Right, and also raised important questions
about non-profit institutions that have an endowment and you try to make
a lot of money and then with the funds do you do
make more conservative. The big thing about turning over the tables of
the money changers. What does it do to the respect of הקדש
Hekdesh if you're in the profit, in the business of making the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash a business, the business of making money? It
completely de-animates the part to do with the returns of the market.
Well, there you go. Okay. So, and we have a set of
hot benches over here. Really? The concept of קיץ המזבח Keitz HaMizbeach
is like לשון להקיץ, lashon l'hakitz, right,
to
wake it up.
So,
yeah,
or
some say it means like the word like קיץ, kayitz, like the
summer, like it's sort of on summer vacation and you don't want
it to be on vacation, in the same... Ah.
And the figs, that you would have them dried out. Dessert.
Ah. Small words matter.
Like, yeah, like the
מוקצה. muktzah. Yeah, yeah, at the
edge, at the edge.